If you've been thinking about US politics
إذا كنتم تفكرون في السياسة الأمريكية
and trying to make sense of it for the last year or so,
وتحاولون فهم ما جرى في السنة الأخيرة أو نحو ذلك،
you might have hit on something like the following three propositions:
فإنكم بذلك قد وجدتم شيئًا يشبه الافتراضات الثلاثة التالية:
one, US partisanship has never been so bad before;
الأول، لم تكن السياسة الحزبية في أمريكا بهذا السوء أبدًا من قبل،
two,
والثاني،
for the first time, it's geographically spatialized --
لأول مرة، تكونُ جغرافية مكانية،
we're divided between the coasts, which want to look outwards,
نحنُ منقسمون بين السواحل التي ترغبُ في النظر نحو الخارج،
and the center of the country, which wants to look inwards;
ومركز البلاد الذي يرغبُ في النظر نحو الداخل،
and third,
والثالث،
there's nothing we can do about it.
لا يوجدُ ما يمكننا عمله حيال ذلك.
I'm here to today to say that all three of these propositions,
وإنني هنا اليوم لأقول لكم بأن جميع الافتراضات الثلاثة،
all of which sound reasonable,
والتي تبدو معقولة،
are not true.
ليست صحيحة.
In fact,
في الحقيقة،
our US partisanship goes all the way back
تعودُ الحزبية الأمريكية إلى الوراء طوال الطريق
to the very beginning of the republic.
إلى بداية الجمهورية.
It was geographically spatialized in almost eerily the same way
كان يحددها جغرافية المكان قديمًا بنفس الطريقة المخيفة تقريبًا
that it is today,
كما هي اليوم،
and it often has been throughout US history.
وكانت كذلك معظم الوقت طوال تاريخ أمريكا.
And last,
وأخيرًا،
and by far most importantly,
والأهم من ذلك كثيرًا،
we actually have an extraordinary mechanism
لدينا في الحقيقة آلية غير عادية
that's designed to help us manage factional disagreement and partisanship.
التي صُممت لمساعدتنا للتعامل مع الخلافات التعصبية والحزبية.
That technology is the Constitution.
هذه الآلية هي "الدستور".
And this is an evolving, subtly, supplely designed entity
وهو كيانٌ مُصمم متطور، وفعّال ومرن
that has the specific purpose
لديه هدف محدد
of teaching us how to manage factional disagreement
ليعلّمنا كيف نتعامل مع الخلافات التعصبية
where it's possible to do that,
وأين يمكننا القيام بذلك،
and giving us techniques for overcoming that disagreement
ويعطينا آليات للتغلب على هذا الخلاف
when that's possible.
عندما يكون ذلك ممكنًا.
Now, in order to tell you the story,
الآن، لأقول لكم القصة،
I want to go back to a pivotal moment in US history,
أرغبُ في العودة إلى لحظة مهمة حاسمة في تاريخ أمريكا،
and that is the moment
وهي تلك اللحظة
when factional disagreement and partisanship was born.
التي تم فيها ظهور الخلافات التعصبية والحزبية.
There actually was a birth moment --
كانت في الحقيقة لحظة ولادة
a moment in US history when partisanship snapped into place.
لحظة في تاريخ أمريكا عندما تفككت الحزبية في مكانها.
The person who's at the core of that story is James Madison.
يُدعى الشخص الذي هو محور هذه القصة (جيمس ماديسون).
And at the moment that this began,
ومنذ أن بدأت تلك اللحظة،
James Madison was riding high.
امتطى (جيمس ماديسون) العُلا.
He himself was the Einstein of not only the US Constitution,
كان بمثاية (اينشتاين) ليس فقط لوضعه الدستور الأمريكي،
but of constitutional thought more globally,
لكن للفكر الدستوري على المستوى العالمي.
and, to give him his due,
ولنعطيه حقه،
he knew it.
علم بذلك.
In a period of time of just three years,
في فترة ثلاثة أعوام فقط،
from 1785 to 1788,
من عام 1785 إلى عام 1788،
he had conceived, theorized, designed, passed and gotten ratified
حدّد، وأصدر، وصممّ، ومرّر، وحصل على التصديق
the US Constitution.
للدستور الأمريكي.
And just to give you some sense of the enormity
ولأعطيكم لمحة حول الشعور بضخامة
of what that accomplishment actually was,
ذلك الإنجاز الذي كان في الواقع،
although Madison couldn't have known it at the time,
ولم يكن يعرفه (ماديسون) في ذلك الوقت،
today that same constitutional technology that he invented is still in use
فما زال يُستخدم نفس تقينة الدستور الذي ابتكره إلى هذا اليوم
not only in the US,
ليس فقط في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
but, 230 years later,
ولكن، وبعد 230 عامًا،
in places like Canada,
في أماكن مثل كندا،
India,
والهند،
South Africa,
وجنوب أفريقيا،
Brazil.
والبرازيل.
So in an extraordinary range of contexts all over the world,
لذلك، ففي نطاق استثنائي غير عادي للسياقات في كل أنحاء العالم،
this technology is still the dominant,
لا تزال هذه الآلية هي المهيمنة،
most used, most effective technology to manage governance.
والأكثر استخداماً، والآلية الأكثر فعالية لإدارة الحكومات.
In that moment,
في تلك اللحظة،
Madison believed that, having solved this problem,
اعتقد (ماديسون) بأن حل هذه المشكلة،
the country would run smoothly,
سيجعل البلاد تسيرُ بسلاسة،
and that he had designed a technology
وبأنه صممّ آلية
that would minimize the results of factions
من شأنها تقليل نتائج التحزب السياسي ووجود الفصائل المختلفة
so there would be no political parties.
وبذلك لن يكون هناك أحزابًا سياسية.
Remarkably, he thought he had designed a constitution
اعتقد وبشكلْ ملحوظ أنه صممّ الدستور
that was against political parties
الذي كان ضد وجود الأحزاب السياسية
and would make them unnecessary.
مما سيجعلها غير ضرورية.
He had gotten an enormous degree of help
قد حصل على درجة كبيرة من المساعدة
in the final marketing phase of his constitutional project
في مرحلة التسويق النهائية من مشروعه الدستوري
from a man you may have heard of, called Alexander Hamilton.
من رجل أعتقدُ أنكم سمعتم به، يدعى (ألكسندر هاميلتون).
Now, Hamilton was everything Madison was not.
الآن، كان (هاميلتون) عكس (ماديسون) في كل شيء.
He was passionate, where Madison was restrained.
كان عاطفيًا، بينما كان ماديسون مسيطرًا على نفسه.
He was pansexual,
كان متعدد الميول الجنسي،
where Madison didn't speak to a woman except for once
بينما لم يتحدث (ماديسون) إلى امرأة إلا في مرة واحدة
until he was 42 years old,
عندما بلغ من العمر 42 عامًا
and then married Dolley and lived happily ever after for 40 years.
ومن ثم تزوج (دوللي)، وعاش سعيدًا بعد ذلك لمدة 40 عاماً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
To put it bluntly,
لأقولها صراحة،
Hamilton's the kind of person
كان (هاميلتون) نوعًا من الأشخاص
about whom you would write a hip-hop musical --
ممن ستكتب حوله موسيقى الهيب-هوب --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and Madison is the kind of person
و(ماديسون) هو نوع من الأشخاص
about whom you would not write a hip-hop musical.
ممن لا تكتب حوله موسيقى الهيب-هوب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or indeed, a musical of any kind at all.
أو في الواقع، أي نوع آخر من الموسيقى.
But together,
لكنهما معًا،
they had become a rather unlikely pairing,
أصبحا ثنائيًا من غير المحتمل أن يحدث،
and they had produced the Federalist Papers,
وكتبا "أوراق الفيديراليست"
which offered a justification
والتي قدّمت تبريرًا
and, as I mentioned,
وكما ذكرتُ سابقًا،
a marketing plan for the Constitution,
خطة تسويقية لترويج الدستور،
which had been wildly effective and wildly successful.
الذي كان فعالًا وناجحًا على نطاق واسع.
Once the new government was in place,
وحالما تسلّمت الحكومة الجديدة زمام الحكم،
Hamilton became Secretary of the Treasury,
أصبح (هامليتون) وزيرًا للخزانة،
and he had a very specific idea in mind.
وكان لديه فكرة محددّة في الاعتبار.
And that was
وكانت،
to do for financial institutions and infrastructure
العمل من أجل المؤسسات المالية، والبنية التحتية،
exactly what Madison had done for constitutions.
تمامًا كما عمل (ماديسون) من أجل الدساتير،
Again, his contemporaries all knew it.
مرةً أخرى، عرف معاصروه كل شيء.
One of them told Madison,
أخبر أحدهم (ماديسون)،
who can't have liked it very much,
الذي لم يرغب في الدساتير كثيرًا،
that Hamilton was the Newton of infrastructure.
بأن (هامليتون) كان بمثابة (نيوتن) بالنسبة إلى البنية التحتية.
The idea was pretty straightforward.
كانت الفكرة مباشرة وصريحة جدًا.
Hamilton would give the United States a national bank,
رغب (هاميلتون) في اعطاء أمريكا بنكًا قوميًا،
a permanent national debt --
ديونًا قومية دائمة --
he said it would be "immortal," his phrase --
قال بأن الأمر سيكون "خالدًا إلى الأبد" هذه عبارته --
and a manufacturing policy that would enable trade and manufacturing
وأن سياسة التصنيع التي ستمكنُ التجارة والتصنيع
rather than agriculture,
أكثر من الزراعة،
which was where the country's primary wealth had historically been.
حيثُ كانت الثروة الأساسية للبلاد تاريخيًا.
Madison went utterly ballistic.
أصبح (ماديسون) عاضبًا وهائجًا تماماً.
And in this pivotal, critical decision,
وفي هذا القرار المحوري الحاسم،
instead of just telling the world that his old friend Hamilton was wrong
فبدلًا من أن يخبر العالم بأن صديقه القديم (هاميلتون) كان خاطئًا
and was adopting the wrong policies,
وأنه تبنّى سياسات خاطئة،
he actually began to argue
بدأ في الحقيقة يجادل ويناقش
that Hamilton's ideas were unconstitutional --
بأن أفكار (هاميلتون) غير دستورية --
that they violated the very nature of the Constitution
وأنها انتهكت طبيعة الدستور
that the two of them had drafted together.
الذي قاما معًا بكتابة مسودته.
Hamilton responded the way you would expect.
كانت ردة فعل (هاميلتون) بنفس الطريقة التي تتوقعونها.
He declared Madison to be his "personal and political enemy" --
صرّح بأن (ماديسون) سيكون "عدوه الشخصي والسياسي" --
these are his words.
هذه هي كلماته.
So these two founders who had been such close friends and such close allies
حتى أن هذين المؤسـسين الذين كانا صديقين قريبين، وحليفين قريبين،
and such partners,
وشريكين،
then began to produce enmity.
بدآ في اظهار العداوة بينهما.
And they did it in the good, old-fashioned way.
وقاما بها جيدًا وبالطريقة القديمة.
First, they founded political parties.
أولًا، أوجدا الأحزاب السياسية.
Madison created a party originally called the Democratic Republican Party --
شكّل (ماديسون) حزبًا أطلق عليه في الأصل اسم "الحزب الجمهوري الديمقراطي" --
"Republican" for short --
"الجمهوري" للاختصار--
and Hamilton created a party called the Federalist Party.
وشكّل (هاميلتون) حزبًا أطلق عليه اسم "الحزب الفيدرالي".
Those two parties adopted positions on national politics
تبنى كلا الحزبين مواقف بشأن السياسة القومية
that were extreme and exaggerated.
التي كانت متطرفة ومبالغ فيها.
To give you a clear example:
لأعطيكم مثالًا واضحًا:
Madison, who had always believed
(ماديسون)، الذي اعتقد دومًا
that the country would have some manufacturing and some trade
بأنه سيكون لدى البلاد بعض التصنيع والتجارة
and some agriculture,
وبعض الزراعة،
began attacking Hamilton
بدأ في مهاجمة (هاميلتون)
as a kind of tool of the financial markets
كنوع من أداة الأسواق المالية
whom Hamilton himself intended to put in charge of the country.
الذي كان (هاميلتون) نفسه المقصود في تولي زمام حكم البلاد.
That was an overstatement,
كان ذلك مبالغًا فيه،
but it was something Madison came to believe.
ولكنه أصبح شيئًا يؤمنُ (ماديسون) به.
He also attacked city life,
كما أنه هاجم حياة المدينة
and he said that the coasts were corrupt,
وقال بأن مناطق السواحل فاسدة.
and what people needed to do was to look inwards
وما تحتاجُ إليه الناس هو النظر نحو الداخل
to the center of the country,
إلى مركز البلاد
to farmers, who were the essence of Republican virtue,
إلى المزارعين الذين هم جوهر فضيلة الجمهوريين
and they should go back to the values that had made American great,
وأن عليهم العودة إلى القيم التي جعلت أمريكا عظيمة
specifically the values of the Revolution,
تحديدًا قيم الثورة،
and those were the values of low taxes,
وتلك هي قيم الضرائب المنخفضة،
agriculture
والعودة إلى الزراعة،
and less trade.
وانخفاض التجارة.
Hamilton responded to this by saying that Madison was naïve,
ردّ (هاميلتون) على ذلك قائلًا، أنّ (ماديسون) كان ساذجًا،
that he was childish,
وكان صبيانيًا،
and that his goal was to turn the United States
وكان هدفه تحويل الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
into a primitive autarchy,
إلى سيادة الحكم الذاتي البدائي،
self-reliant and completely ineffectual on the global scale.
معتمدة على ذاتها وغير فعالة تمامًا على المستوى العالمي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They both meant it,
قصد كلاهما ذلك،
and there was some truth to each of their claims,
وكانت هناك بعض الحقيقة في إدعاءات كلٍ منهما،
because each side was grossly exaggerating the views of the other
لأن كل جانب كان يبالغُ بشكلْ كبير في وجهات نظر الآخر
in order to fight their war.
للدفاع عن الصراع القائم بينهما.
They founded newspapers,
أسـسا صحفًا،
and so for the first time in US history,
لأول مرة في تاريخ أمريكا.
the news that people received came entirely through the lens
جاءت الأخبار التي تلقاها الناس من خلال وجهات نظر
of either the Republican or the Federalist party.
كلٍ من الحزبين الجمهوري والفيدرالي.
How does this end?
كيف انتهى ذلك؟
Well, as it turned out, the Constitution did its work.
حسنًا، كما تبين، قد قام الدستور بعمله.
But it did its work in surprising ways
ولكنه قام بذلك بوسائل مدهشة
that Madison himself had not fully anticipated.
حتى لم يتوقع (ماديسون) نفسه ذلك بالكامل.
First, there was a series of elections.
أولًا، كان هناك سلسلة من الانتخابات.
And the first two times out of the box,
وكانت نتيجة الاقتراع لأول مرتين،
the Federalists destroyed the Republicans.
أن الفيدراليين قد هزموا الجمهوريين.
Madison was astonished.
كان (ماديسون) مندهشًا.
Of course, he blamed the press.
بطبيعة الحال، اتهم وسائل الاعلام.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And in a rather innovative view --
وفي وجهة نظر مبتكرة نوعًا ما --
Madison never failed to innovate when he thought about anything --
لم يفشل (ماديسون) أبدًا عندما كان يفكر في شيء ما --
he said the reason that the press was so pro-Federalist
قال ان السبب وراء تأييد الصحافة المطلق للحزب الفدرالي
is that the advertisers were all Federalists,
هو أن جميع المعلنين كانوا فيدراليين،
because they were traders on the coasts who got their capital from Britain,
ولأنهم كانوا تجارًا من السواحل، ويحصلون على رأسمالهم من بريطانيا،
which Federalism was in bed with.
التي كان الحزب الفيدرالي على علاقة سرية معهم.
That was his initial explanation.
كان ذلك تفسيره الأولي.
But despite the fact that the Federalists,
لكن وعلى الرغم من حقيقة أن الفيدراليين،
once in power,
فور وصولهم إلى سدة الحكم،
actually enacted laws that criminalized criticism of the government --
أصدروا في الواقع قوانين تجّرم انتقاد الحكومة --
that happened in the United States --
التي حدثت في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية --
nevertheless,
مع ذلك،
the Republicans fought back,
حارب الجمهوريون ذلك،
and Madison began to emphasize the freedom of speech,
وبدأ (ماديسون) في التأكيد على حرية التعبير،
which he had built into the Bill of Rights,
التي اعتمدها في "وثيقة الحقوق"،
and the capacity of civil society
وقدرة المجتمع المدني
to organize.
للتنظيم.
And sure enough, nationally,
ومن المؤكد بما فيه الكفاية، وعلى الصعيد القومي،
small local groups -- they were called Democratic-Republican Societies --
فإن مجموعات محلية صغيرة، أطلق عليها اسم "مجتمعات جمهورية ديمقراطية" --
began to form and protest against Federalist-dominated hegemony.
بدأت في التشكّل والتظاهر ضد سيطرة الهيمنة الفيدرالية.
Eventually, the Republicans managed to win a national election --
في النهاية، تمكّن الجمهوريون من الفوز في الانتخابات الوطنية--
that was in 1800.
التي كانت في عام 1800.
Madison became the Secretary of State,
وأصبح (ماديسون) وزيرًا للخارجية،
his friend and mentor Jefferson became president,
وأصبح معلمه وصديقة (جفرسون) رئيسًا،
and they actually, over time,
وفي الواقع، ومع مرور الوقت،
managed to put the Federalists completely out of business.
تمكّنا من وضع الفيدرالين بالكامل خارج اللعبة السياسية.
That was their goal.
كان ذلك هدفهما.
Now, why did that happen?
الآن، لماذا حدث ذلك؟
It happened because in the structure of the Constitution
حدث ذلك لأنه وفي سياق هيكلة الدستور
were several features that actually managed faction
كان هناك عدة ميزات تعاملت في الواقع مع التحزب والفصائل
the way there were supposed to do in the first place.
بالطريقة التي كان من المفترض القيام بها في المقام الأول.
What were those?
ما هي تلك الميزات؟
One -- most important of all --
الأولى -- وأهم واحدة على الإطلاق --
the freedom of speech.
حرية التعبير.
This was an innovative idea at the time.
كانت فكرة مبتكرة في ذلك الوقت.
Namely, that if you were out of power,
تحديدًا، إذا كان أحدكم خارج نطاق السلطة،
you could still say that the government was terrible.
لا يزالُ بامكانه القول أن الحكومة كانت فظيعة.
Two,
الثانية،
civil society organization.
المؤسسات المجتمعية المدنية.
The capacity to put together private groups, individuals,
القدرة لوضع المجموعات الخاصة، والأفراد،
political parties and others
والأحزاب السياسية وغيرها معًا
who would organize to try to bring about fundamental change.
الذين ينتظمون في محاولة لجلب وتحقيق التغيير الأساسي.
Perhaps most significantly was the separation of powers --
وربما الأهم من ذلك هو فصل السلطات --
an extraordinary component of the Constitution.
الذي هو عنصر استثنائي من الدستور.
The thing about the separation of powers
فالشيء حول فصل السلطات
is that it did then and it does now,
هو أنه حصل سابقًا ويحصل الآن،
drive governance to the center.
لتحريك الحكومة نحو المركز.
You can get elected to office in the United States
يمكنُ لأي أحدٍ منكم أن يُنتخب رئيسًا في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
with help from the periphery,
بمساعدة من المحيط،
right or left.
اليمين أو اليسار.
It turns out,
لقد تبين،
you actually can't govern unless you bring on board the center.
لا يمكنُ لأحدكم أن يحكم في الفعل ما لم يجلب المركز له.
There are midterm elections that come incredibly fast
تحدثُ انتخابات في منتصف المدة بسرعة رهيبة
after a presidency begins.
بعد أن تبدأ الرئاسة.
Those drive presidents towards the center.
تحركُ هذه الميزات الرؤساء اتجاه المركز.
There's a structure in which the president, in fact, does not rule
في الواقع، هناك هيكلة ما تجعل الرئيس لا يسيطر،
or even govern,
أو حتى أن يحكم،
but can only propose laws which other people have to agree with --
لكن يمكنه أن يقترح القوانين فقط، التي يتعينُ على الآخرين الموافقة عليها --
another feature that tends to drive presidents
وهناك ميزة أخرى من شأنها دفع الرؤساء
who actually want to get things done
ممن يريدون فعلًا انجاز الأمور
to the center.
نحو المركز.
And a glance at the newspapers today will reveal to you
وستكشف لكم لمحة سريعة في صحف اليوم
that these principles are still completely in operation.
بأنه لا تزال هذه المبادىء تعملُ بالكامل حتى يومنا هذا.
No matter how a president gets elected,
وبعض النظر كيف تم انتخاب الرئيس،
the president cannot get anything done
فلا يمكنُ له انجاز أي شيء
unless the president first of all follows the rules of the Constitution,
إلا إذا اتبع أولًا قوانين وقواعد الدستور،
because if not,
لأنه إذا لم يفعل ذلك،
the courts will stand up, as indeed has sometimes occurred,
ستقفُ المحاكم كما حدث في الواقع في بعض الأحيان،
not only recently, but in the past, in US history.
ليس فقط مؤخرًا، ولكن في الماضي، في التاريخ الأمريكي.
And furthermore,
وبالإضافة إلى ذلك،
the president needs people,
يحتاجُ الرئيس إلى الناس،
elected officials who know they need to win election
وإلى مسؤولين منتخبين ممن يعرفون أنهم بحاجة للفوز في الانتخابات
from centrist voters,
من الناخبين الوسطيين،
also to back his or her policies in order to pass laws.
ودعم سياساته أو سياساتها من أجل تمرير القوانين.
Without it, nothing much happens.
من دون ذلك، لا يحدث الكثير،
The takeaway of this brief excursus
العبرة من هذه الحكاية المُختصرة
into the history of partisanship, then, is the following:
في تاريخ الأحزاب السياسية، بعد ذلك، هي التالي:
partisanship is real;
التحزب والأحزاب السياسية هي حقيقة،
it's profound;
وعميقة،
it's extraordinarily powerful,
وإنها فعاّلة للغاية،
and it's terribly upsetting.
ومزعجة بشكل رهيب.
But the design of the Constitution is greater than partisanship.
لكن تصميم الدستور أكبر من التحزب والأحزاب السياسية.
It enables us to manage partisanship when that's possible,
يمكّننا الدستور من التعامل مع التحزب عندما يكون ذلك ممكنًا،
and it enables us actually to overcome partisan division
ويمكّننا في الحقيقة التغلب على الانقسام الحزبي
and produce compromise,
وإيجاد حل وسطي توفيقي،
when and only when that is possible.
عندما يكون ذلك ممكنًا فقط.
A technology like that is a technology that worked
تقنية مثل هذه هي الآلية التي عملت
for the founders,
من أجل مؤسـسيها،
it worked for their grandchildren,
وعملت لأحفادهم،
it didn't work at the moment of the Civil War,
ولم تعمل في فترة الحرب الأهلية،
but then it started working again.
وثم بدأت تعمل مجددًا.
And it worked for our grandparents,
وعملت من أجل أجدادنا،
our parents,
وآبائنا،
and it's going to work for us.
وستعملُ لنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So what you should do is really simple.
لذلك فما عليكم القيام به هو بسيط حقًا.
Stand up for what you believe in,
انهضوا ودافعوا عمّا تؤمنون به،
support the organizations that you care about,
ادعموا المنظات التي تهتمون بها،
speak out on the issues that matter to you,
وتحدثوا عاليًا حول القضايا التي تهمكم،
get involved,
شاركوا،
make change,
اصنعوا التغيير،
express you opinion,
عبّروا عن آرائكم،
and do it with respect and knowledge and confidence
وقوموا بذلك بكل احترام وعن معرفة وثقة
that it's only by working together
وبالعمل معًا فقط
that the constitutional technology can do the job that it is designed to do.
يمكن لللآلية الدستورية أن تقوم بوظيفتها التي صُممت من أجلها.
Stand up for what you believe,
انهضوا لما تؤمنون به،
but take a deep breath while you do it.
ولكن تريثوا وأنتم تقومون بذلك.
It's going to be OK.
ستكون الأمور على ما يرام.
Thanks.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)